ANNA FARIHA

Homepage: afariha.github.io
Email: anna.fariha.bd@gmail.com

RESEARCH INTEREST

The aim of my research is to democratize data and data-driven systems towards boosting productivity and enhancing transparency. To this end, my research focuses on three key aspects of data system democratization: enhancing usability of data systems for both non-experts and experts, providing explanation frameworks to enable understanding of system behavior, and achieving trust and fairness in data-driven machine learning.

- Data systems usability: query by example, data summarization, data discovery, data cleaning.
- Metadata management and its applications: data constraints, data drift, trusted machine learning.
- Causal reasoning and explanation frameworks: root cause analysis of nondeterministic bugs, interventional debugging, data debugging, explaining data non-conformance, fair classification.

EDUCATION

• Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science (2021)

College of Information and Computer Sciences, University of Massachusetts, Amherst Dissertation title: Enhancing Usability and Explainability of Data Systems

- o Advisor: Alexandra Meliou
- o Committee members: Emery Berger (UMass), Peter Haas (UMass), Suman Nath (MSR)
- \circ CGPA: 4.00 (in the scale of 4.00)
- Master of Science in Computer Science (2020)

College of Information and Computer Sciences, University of Massachusetts, Amherst

- o CGPA: 4.00 (in the scale of 4.00)
- \bullet Master of Science in Computer Science and Engineering (2011)

University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

- o CGPA: 4.00 (in the scale of 4.00)
- Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engineering (2010)

University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

o CGPA: 3.83 (in the scale of 4.00)

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

• Researcher (June 2021 – present)

PROSE (Programming by Examples and Natural Language) Research & Engineering Group Microsoft, Redmond, WA

• Research Assistant (September 2016 – May 2021)

Data Systems Research for Exploration, Analytics, and Modeling (DREAM) Lab University of Massachusetts Amherst, MA

- **Research Intern** (Summer 2019 & 2018)
 - PROSE Research & Engineering, Microsoft (Mentor: Ashish Tiwari)
 - DMX Lab, Microsoft Research, Redmond (Mentor: Suman Nath)
- Teaching Faculty (Lecturer) (2012 2016)
 - Computer Science and Engineering, University of Dhaka, Bangladesh (2014 2016)
 - Computer Science and Engineering, United International University, Bangladesh (2012 2014)

HONORS, AWARDS, & GRANTS

- VLDB Best Demonstration Runner-up award, 2020
- Microsoft Research Dissertation Grant, 2020 (\$25,000 USD for academic year 2020-21)
- Travel and accommodation award in CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop, Washington DC, 2017
- Jim Gray scholarship, CICS, UMass Amherst, 2016
- Special Achievement Award Bangladesh ICT Journalist Forum & Bangladesh Women in IT, 2012
- Special Achievement Award for outstanding performances in programming contests, U Dhaka, 2011
- Dean's Honor Award and Dean's Award Faculty of Engineering, University of Dhaka (top 1%), 2010
- Fatema-Iqbal trust scholarship, University of Dhaka, 2008
- Best Student of the School (Kushtia Govt. Girls' High School), 2003
- National Education Board Scholarship: 12th grade, 10th grade, 8th grade, & 5th grade

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. E Rezig, A Bhandari, A Fariha, B Price, A Vanterpool, A Bowne, L McEvoy, V Gadepally: Examples are All You Need: Iterative Data Discovery by Example in Data Lakes. (abstract) <u>CIDR</u> 2022.
- 2. S Galhotra, A Fariha, R Lourenço, J Freire, A Meliou, D Srivastava: DataExposer: Exposing Disconnect between Data and Systems. (under revision) SIGMOD 2022.
- 3. MT Islam, A Fariha, A Meliou, B Salimi: Through the Data Management Lens: Experimental Analysis and Evaluation of Fair Classification. (under revision) <u>SIGMOD</u> 2022.
- 4. N Yadav, M Brucato, A Fariha, O Youngquist, J Killingback, A Meliou, PJ Haas: SubSumE: A Dataset for Subjective Summary Extraction from Wikipedia Documents. <u>NewSum@EMNLP</u> 2021.
- 5. E Rezig, A Bhandari, A Fariha, B Price, A Vanterpool, V Gadepally, M Stonebraker: DICE: Data Discovery by Example. (demo paper) VLDB 2021.
- 6. A Fariha, A Tiwari, A Meliou, A Radhakrishna, S Gulwani. CoCo: Interactive Exploration of Conformance Constraints for Data Understanding and Data Cleaning. (demo paper) <u>SIGMOD</u> 2021.
- 7. A Fariha, A Tiwari, A Radhakrishna, S Gulwani, A Meliou. Conformance Constraint Discovery: Measuring Trust in Data-Driven Systems. <u>SIGMOD</u> 2021.
- 8. A Fariha, S Nath, A Meliou. Causality-guided Adaptive Interventional Debugging. <u>SIGMOD</u> 2020
- 9. A Fariha, M Brucato, PJ Haas, A Meliou. SuDocu: Summarizing Documents by Example. (demo paper) VLDB 2020 (Best demonstration runner-up award).
- 10. A Fariha, A Tiwari, A Radhakrishna, S Gulwani. ExTuNe: Explaining Tuple Non-conformance. (demo paper) <u>SIGMOD</u> 2020.
- 11. A Fariha, A Meliou. Example-Driven Query Intent Discovery: Abductive Reasoning using Semantic Similarity. VLDB 2019.
- 12. A Fariha, SM Sarwar, A Meliou. SQuID: Semantic Similarity-Aware Query Intent Discovery. (demo paper) <u>SIGMOD</u> 2018.
- 13. A Fariha, CF Ahmed, CK Leung, M Samiullah, S Pervin, L Cao. A New Framework for Mining Frequent Interaction Patterns from Meeting Databases. <u>Engineering Applications of Artificial</u> Intelligence 2015.
- 14. A Fariha, CF Ahmed, CK Leung, SM Abdullah, L Cao: Mining Frequent Patterns from Human Interactions in Meetings Using Directed Acyclic Graphs. <u>PAKDD</u> 2013.

SERVICE & OUTREACH

- Round Table Chair: Interactive Querying and Visualization for Large Data, VLDB 2021
- Session Chair: Learning and Explainability, EDBT 2021
- Program committee member:
 - o SIGMOD 2022 (research track)
 - o VLDB 2022 (research track)
 - o SIGMOD 2021 (research track)
 - o EDBT 2021 (demonstration track)
 - o VLDB 2021 (demonstration track)
- External reviewer: SIGMOD 2018, 2019, and 2020; CHI 2021; UIST 2021; The VLDB Journal
- Mentor: Research Experience for Undergraduate Students (REU), UMass, Summer 2017
- Volunteer: Girls Inc. Eureka! Workshop, Summer 2017; WECode, Harvard University, 2017

INVITED TALKS

- MIT CSAIL, Semantic data management reading group: October 2021
- CIS, University of Pennsylvania: February 2021
- DATA Lab, Northeastern University: January 2021
- Microsoft: January 2021

COMPETITIVE PROGRAMMING & PROBLEM SOLVING

| Event | Position | Team | Year |
|--|----------|--------------|------|
| ACM ICPC (Dhaka Regional, Bangladesh) | 5 | DU Resonance | 2011 |
| IUT ICT Fest Programming Contest (Dhaka, Bangladesh) | 1 | DU Resonance | 2011 |
| DU NCPC (Dhaka, Bangladesh) | 1 | DU Resonance | 2011 |
| DU NCPC – Women (Dhaka, Bangladesh) | 1 | DU Felicity | 2011 |
| ACM ICPC (Amritapuri Regional, India) | 6 | DU Resonance | 2010 |
| ACM ICPC (Dhaka Regional, Bangladesh) | 4 | DU Resonance | 2010 |
| ACM ICPC (Dhaka Regional, Bangladesh) | 3 | DU Ouranos | 2009 |

Problem Setter & Judge

- SAARC Programming Contest, 2014 & 2013, Bangladesh University
- Bangladesh Informatics Olympiad, 2013, National Round
- ACM ICPC Dhaka Site, 2012, Daffodil International University